What exactly is the heap, what does malloc really do?
堆到底是什么，malloc到底是做什么的？
Those are questions we try to answer in this video.
这些是我们在这段视频中试图回答的问题。
You may have learned that when you are programming and you need some, more memory you might use
你可能已经知道，当你在编程时，你需要一些，更多的内存，你可能会使用
the heap, by allocating memory with malloc and if you are done you free it again.
堆，通过使用malloc分配内存，如果完成了，就可以再次释放它。
And somehow, some magic is happening and you don’t really know how you magically get
不知怎么的，一些魔法正在发生，你不知道你是如何神奇地得到的。
more memory or give it back.
更多的记忆或者把它还给我。
Before we talk about malloc, let’s first talk about how our process gets any memory
在我们讨论malloc之前，我们先讨论一下我们的进程如何获得任何内存。
in the first place.
首先。
This is done via mmap or brk.
这是通过mmap或brk完成的。
Those are system calls, which means we ask the kernel directly.
这些是系统调用，这意味着我们直接询问内核。
mmap asks the kernel give us some new virtual address space, basically requesting a new
mmap请求内核给我们一些新的虚拟地址空间，基本上请求一个新的
memory segment.
内存段。
Besides mmap there is also brk, which can be used to change the size of an already used
除了mmap之外，还有brk，可以用来改变已经使用的
This is real fucking magic.
这是真正的魔法。
In the end the process doesn’t care how this memory is implemented - if there is RAM,
最后，这个过程并不关心这个内存是如何实现的-如果有RAM，
and where exactly on the ram you store it, or if you have a SWAP file because you don’t
在RAM上的确切位置存储它，或者如果您有一个交换文件，因为您没有
have enough RAM.
有足够的内存。
The kernel and hardware takes care of this, and maps that memory into the process, this
内核和硬件负责处理这个问题，并将内存映射到进程中，
means that the process can transparently access those memory addresses and work with them
意味着进程可以透明地访问这些内存地址并使用它们
- and transparent in this context means, “doesn’t have to know anything about it”.
-在这种情况下，透明意味着“不必知道任何事情”。
You can execute heap1 with strace and you see all those calls to mmap to initially set
您可以使用strace执行heap1，并且可以看到所有对mmap的调用最初设置为
up the processes memory regions.
处理内存区域。
And near the end it uses brk to setup the heap.
最后，它使用brk来设置堆。
So why don’t we just use mmap or brk to get more memory for our process?
那么，我们为什么不使用mmap或brk为我们的进程获取更多的内存呢？
And why do we always talk about the heap with malloc and free?
为什么我们总是用malloc和free谈论堆？
Well, malloc is just a very fancy and convenient wrapper that handles that brk or mmapping
好吧，malloc只是一个非常花哨和方便的包装，可以处理BRK或MMAPping
for us.
对我们来说。
And does much more.
做得更多。
Malloc will call mmap or brk to get more memory if the heap doesn’t exist or is too small.
如果堆不存在或太小，malloc将调用mmap或brk以获取更多内存。
But on top of that it will help us to organize and manage that memory.
但除此之外，它将帮助我们组织和管理记忆。
Also during CTF challenges, and the example we will have a look at shortly, use the heap
同样，在CTF挑战期间，以及我们稍后将看到的示例中，使用堆
so little, that we won’t see any additional memory mapped regions.
如此之少，我们将看不到任何额外的内存映射区域。
So to keep things simple, we consider the heap to be, just a big chunk of fixed memory
为了简单起见，我们认为堆只是一大块固定内存
mapped memory.
映射内存。
And we can do in this memory whatever we want.
在这个记忆中，我们可以做任何我们想做的事。
So when we refer to the heap, we actually mean this memory region.
所以当我们提到堆时，实际上是指这个内存区域。
So what does it mean that malloc will manage the heap?
那么，malloc将管理堆意味着什么呢？
Let’s explore this abstractly first.
让我们先抽象地探讨一下这个问题。
We want to allocate 8 bytes.
我们要分配8个字节。
So we call malloc with 8.
所以我们用8来称呼malloc。
This means we block 8 bytes on the heap.
这意味着我们在堆上阻塞了8个字节。
Each call to malloc will return the address of the heap where the area got blocked, and
对malloc的每个调用都将返回区域被阻塞的堆的地址，以及
with this address we know where we can write our 8 bytes to.
有了这个地址，我们就知道在哪里可以写入8个字节。
So we can now write the string “AAAABBBB” to that address.
现在我们可以将字符串“aaaabbb”写入该地址。
Now we allocate two more times.
现在我们再分配两次。
malloc(8), malloc(8).
malloc（8），malloc（8）。
This begs the question what does blocking mean.
这就引出了一个问题：阻塞意味着什么。
And how does malloc know what address to return?
Malloc如何知道返回的地址？
If I would hire you to write me a program that gives me an address of memory I can use
如果我雇你给我写一个程序，给我一个我可以使用的内存地址
safely for different sizes, you could come up with a working solution.
对于不同的尺寸，您可以安全地提出一个有效的解决方案。
And if you would implement that you would have created your own heap algorithm.
如果您实现了这一点，那么您将创建自己的堆算法。
So there are many different ways one could implement that.
所以有很多不同的方法可以实现它。
Though most commonly used is an implementation called DLmalloc.
尽管最常用的是一个名为dlmalloc的实现。
Because a dude with the name Douglas Lea wrote it.
因为是一个叫道格拉斯·李的家伙写的。
And that malloc algorithm will store for each chunk it blocks the size of the chunk right
malloc算法将为它所阻塞的每个块存储块的大小。
before it.
在它之前。
And it will also keep 4 bytes before that empty for how the free is implemented.
它还将保留4个字节，以表示自由是如何实现的。
But we will only focus on malloc for now.
但我们现在只关注malloc。
Let’s do the mallocs again, and let’s think like a computer.
让我们再做一次mallocs，让我们像计算机一样思考。
So at the start, when the first malloc is called, we obviously know the beginning of
所以在开始的时候，当第一个malloc被调用时，我们显然知道
the heap.
堆。
So we store the size that we want to allocate there, and return the address where the chunk
所以我们存储要在那里分配的大小，并返回块所在的地址
part, that is usable by the programmer, starts.
程序员可以使用的部分启动。
Though, how does malloc now know on the next call to malloc where the next chunk can be
但是，malloc现在如何知道下一个调用malloc的位置
placed?
放置？
Not that we write over our previously allocated area.
不是说我们重写了以前分配的区域。
Well we obviously have to kinda memorize where our free region begins.
很明显，我们必须记住自由区的起点。
So malloc will simply do some math, and update the address that pointed to the beginning
所以malloc只需要做一些计算，并更新指向开头的地址
of the heap, by adding the size of the chunk we allocated to it.
通过添加我们分配给堆的块的大小。
And this happens every malloc.
每一个malloc都会发生这种情况。
So there is a pointer somewhere, that will always point to free memory.
所以在某个地方有一个指针，它总是指向空闲内存。
Cool.
酷。
Just for understanding purposes.
只是为了理解目的。
Given the returned address of malloc, what can you do with that?
考虑到malloc的返回地址，你能怎么处理？
Well, this pointer points to the start where we can write data to.
好吧，这个指针指向我们可以写入数据的起点。
So if we look at the address just before that, we can read the size of the current chunk.
因此，如果我们在这之前查看地址，就可以读取当前块的大小。
And if we know the size, we can add the size to that address to get to the next chunk on
如果我们知道大小，我们可以将大小添加到该地址以访问下一个块
the heap.
堆。
Where we can do the same again.
我们可以再这样做。
Now let’s have a look at the heap level 1 challenge from protostar.
现在让我们来看看来自原恒星的堆级别1挑战。
We will use that example to look at how malloc works in real-life.
我们将用这个例子来看看malloc在现实生活中是如何工作的。
But first let’s step through the code line by line and try to imagine how the heap will
但首先，让我们一行一行地遍历代码，并尝试想象堆将如何
look like.
看起来像。
And then next video we actually do that practically.
下一个视频我们实际上是这么做的。
The objective here seems to call winner().
这里的目标似乎称为winner() 。
So we somehow have to redirect code execution to that function.
所以我们必须以某种方式将代码执行重定向到该函数。
At the top there is a struct defined called internet, which has two members, a priority
在顶部有一个名为internet的结构，它有两个成员，一个优先级
integer.
整数。
And the second member is a char pointer called name - Which means name contains a pointer
第二个成员是一个名为name的char指针，也就是说name包含一个指针
to a string somewhere else.
到其他地方的字符串。
Structs are like classes.
结构类似于类。
At least in terms of providing a structure with multiple different member attributes.
至少在提供具有多个不同成员属性的结构方面。
Now, main defines three variables from the type struct internet pointer, but only two
现在，main从类型struct internet指针定义了三个变量，但只有两个变量
are used.
被使用。
I guess a leftover from creating this level.
我想这是创建这个级别的剩余部分。
I emphasize struct internet pointer, because those three internet objects are not stored
我强调结构Internet指针，因为这三个Internet对象没有存储
on the stack.
在堆栈上。
Only the addresses, the pointer, to those objects are stored in i1, i2 and i3.
只有指向这些对象的地址（指针）存储在i1、i2和i3中。
Anyhow, then it starts allocating those objects on the heap.
无论如何，然后它开始在堆上分配这些对象。
It first calls malloc with enough space for the i1 object.
它首先调用malloc，为i1对象提供足够的空间。
Sizeof will return the number of bytes this struct requires.
sizeof将返回此结构所需的字节数。
In this case that’s 8, because the integer priority is 4 bytes and the char pointer,
在本例中是8，因为整数优先级是4个字节和char指针，
which is an address, is also 4 bytes.
它是一个地址，也是4个字节。
Because we are on a 32bit machine.
因为我们在32位机器上。
And we know that malloc returns the address on the heap that we can now use.
我们知道malloc返回堆中我们现在可以使用的地址。
So i1 points to the start of 8 bytes in memory.
所以I1指向内存中8个字节的开头。
And now we want to set priority to 1, which will write 1 to the first 4 byte of the allocated
现在我们要将优先级设置为1，它将1写入分配的
area.
面积。
Then it allocates another 8 byte, and the resulting address will be stored in the char
然后它再分配8个字节，结果地址将存储在char中
pointer name.
指针名称。
Which is at offset +4 of the i1 object.
它位于i1对象的偏移量+4处。
As a programmer we write i1-&gt;name, to access the name attribute, but implemented is it
作为一个程序员，我们编写i1-&gt；名称来访问name属性，但是实现了它吗？
as simply going to a certain offset of i1, in thise case i1+4 is the location of the
在这种情况下，I1+4是
char pointer name.
字符指针名称。
So now i1-&gt;name will contain an address, which points to the allocated heap area which we
所以现在i1-&gt；名称将包含一个地址，该地址指向我们
just allocated.
刚刚分配。
Those 8 bytes are intended to store a list of characters, a string - the name.
这8个字节用于存储字符列表，一个字符串——名称。
Then the same is done over again for i2.
然后对I2再次进行同样的操作。
We make space for the struct i2.
我们为结构I2腾出空间。
We set its priority to 2.
我们把它的优先级设置为2。
And we allocate another 8 byte for the name string.
我们为名称字符串分配了另外8个字节。
So basically we have now two objects allocated on the heap that we can work with.
所以基本上我们在堆上分配了两个对象，我们可以使用它们。
Next come two strcpys.
接下来是两条街道。
And we know that strcpy is always super suspicious, because there is no length indication and
我们知道strcpy总是非常可疑，因为没有长度指示，而且
we can potentially write more than we have space.
我们可能写得比空间还多。
In this case the internet-name was allocated with only 8 byte, so we could probably write
在这种情况下，Internet名称只分配了8个字节，因此我们可以
over those 8 bytes and really screw up stuff.
超过了8字节，真的搞砸了。
Anyhow, the strcpy will copy the first argument to the name of the i1 object.
无论如何，strcpy会将第一个参数复制到i1对象的名称中。
i1 points to the start of the i1 object, and at offset +4, which is the name, is the address
I1指向I1对象的开始，偏移量+4（即名称）是地址
of the free 8 bytes that were allocated for the string.
为字符串分配的可用8个字节。
So strcpy will take the address stored there and copy the string from argument 1 at that
所以strcpy将获取存储在那里的地址，并从参数1复制字符串。
location.
位置。
And the same thing is happening for the second argument with i2 object.
同样的事情也发生在第二个关于I2对象的争论中。
It will take the address stored at +4 of i2, and attempt to copy there our string.
它将获取存储在i2的+4的地址，并尝试将字符串复制到该地址。
After that, we will printf and then quit the program.
之后，我们将打印f，然后退出程序。
In the next video we will have a look at the heap while we execute this program to understand
在下一个视频中，我们将在执行该程序以了解
how the heap looks in real-life and how we can work with it in gdb.
堆在现实生活中的外观以及我们如何在gdb中使用它。
Oh by the way.
哦，顺便说一下。
I lied.
我撒谎了。
I said the second word would contain the size of the chunk.
我说第二个词将包含块的大小。
Well it does, but also the lowest bit is used to indicate that the PREVIOUS chunk is used.
是的，但最低的位也用来表示使用了前一个块。
Not free.
不是免费的。
That becomes more important for the free() algorithm.
对于free() 算法来说，这变得更加重要。
Thus in our example those numbers values would all be hex 11.
因此在我们的示例中，这些数值都是十六进制11。
I just want to put a small disclaimer here at the end.
我只想在最后写一个小小的免责声明。
I simplified the heap and malloc a lot.
我把堆和malloc简化了很多。
For example I only talked about one pointer pointing at the free area, in reality there
例如，我只讲了一个指向自由区的指针，实际上在那里
is obviously way more to this.
很明显，这是更重要的。
And If we look into the history of exploitation we are currently looking at stuff from more
如果我们研究剥削的历史，我们现在正在研究更多
than 15 years ago - like 2001-ish.
比15年前——比如2001年的ISH。
A lot of the stuff hasn’t changed and the concepts are the same, but a lot of sdtuff
很多东西都没有改变，概念都是一样的，但是很多东西都没有改变。
is also different.
也是不同的。
Todays malloc implementation is based on dlmalloc, but it’s not really the original dlmalloc
今天的malloc实现是基于dlmalloc的，但它不是最初的dlmalloc
anymore - now its usually referred to as ptmalloc.
现在它通常被称为ptmalloc。
And my goal here is to teach you the fundamentals.
我的目标是教你基础知识。
Eventhough this is not 100% correct, you should have now a rough idea what the heap is and
尽管这不是100%正确的，但您现在应该大致了解堆是什么，以及
what to look for and you can transfer this knowledge to any heap implementation.
要查找的内容，您可以将这些知识转移到任何堆实现中。